Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1829 March 5. Alexander Hamilton, Jr. LS to Samuel W[hittelsey] Dana; New York, [New York], 3 pages; Comments on a recent letter from William Plumer to John Q. Adams concerning the 1803-1804 Congress discussing New England seceding over slavery. Notes dissatisfaction over unequal Southern representation and tax benefits and fears that Southern and Western interests outweighed Northern ones. Describes specifics about establishing a separate government. Was told Alexander Hamilton had agreed to attend a "select meeting of the Leading Federalists in New England" to discuss the measures. Asks for specifics about Dana's relationship with Alexander Hamilton, if he had heard of the plan, and who was involved in it. Seeking to defend his father's "Fame" and "refute the Calumny conveyed."
  - 1829 April 28. E[liphalet] Nott ALS; U[nion] C[ollege], [Schenectady, New York], 1 page; Too late to comply with the recipient's request before the Legislature adjourns. May be willing to write an address, similar to the speech he would have made, once he has more time. "But I doubt whether the public are prepared for receiving the views of the subject I have taken - and whether the freedom with which I have spoken would not do injury in certain quarters."
  - 1829. Henry Coughenour AMs; [Lancaster Co., Pennsylvania], 52 pages; Name and date taken from cover; there is no proof that Henry Coughenour penned any of the recipes which are primarily for cakes, pies, preserves, and beers, wines, and liquors. Also includes the names Andrew Kauffm[an], with a later date in the inside cover [1837?], along with the names Magdalena Herr, Miss Courkholder, and David banks elsewhere in the book. Has recipe for "Indian Flatjacks," "Poor mans pound cake," and "A Compleat Cure for the Hieves."
  - 1830-06-09. [Jeremiah] Day ADS to Johanni O Colton [John Owen Colton]; [New Haven, Connecticut], 1 page; Certification of Colton's proficiency in Latin writing. In Latin and signed "Jeromius Day."
  - 1830 February 3. John G. Krummer DS; ANS to Elizabeth Mehaffey; Litiz, Lancaster Co., Pennsylvania, 2 pages [total]; Certificate of commendation from the principal of the Seminary for Young Ladies at Litiz. Includes a note from Krummer to Mehafey calling on her to "prove that the instructions received whilst a pupil at our Seminary have been beneficial to the advancement of your present & future welfare." Encourages dependence on Jesus and the grace of God.
  - 1830 February-1830 March. H[enry] Wharton Griffith ADfs + 4 Printed Docs.; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 22 pages; 15 pages; A printed pamphlet and 2 printed circulars comment on the quarrel between Henry Wharton Griffith and R. Dillon Drake which led to the the duel between William Miller, Jr., and Charles G. Hunter. Several manuscript drafts are included of portions of Charles H. Duryee's pamphlet, which include pen and ink sketches of faces, abstract doodles, and a man in a red jacket and turban[?]. Two manuscript drafts also appear of a public letter, seemingly by Henry W. Griffith, about Drake's initial physical attacks.
  - 1830 March 20. [Committee of the Proprietors] DS to Parlee Keith; [East Bridgewater, Massachusetts], 1 page; Committee of the Proprietors of the East Bridgewater Meetinghouse received payment of Parlee Keith for pew rent. Signed by John A. Whiting, Samuel D. Shaw, Seth Richard, and Alvan Shaw.
  - 1830 March 27. John Biddle ALS to Edward Rutledge; Washington, [D.C.], 2 pages; Unable to give Rutledge information on the value of land claimed by Mr. Portier. Notes that land sales near Green Bay, Wisconsin, are "not frequent" and ideas of the value of land are not settled. If the "bill establishing the Territorial Govt of Huron" passes, it will be near to Portier's land and will increase its value. Provides a rough estimate of value for Portier's farm. "The claim has not yet been acted upon by Congress but probebly will be decided by the H. of Reps during the next week."
  - 1830 May 7. Elijah K[eeler] Bangs ALS to Charles F. Seidel; Phila[delphia, Pennsylvania], 2 pages [total]; Letter written to the principal of the Moravian Seminary at Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. The letter is regarding the poor conduct of Elijah's daughter, Mary Ann Bangs, at the school. He gives the teachers full authority to punish her as deemed proper. On the same sheet, Elijah writes to his daughter, Mary Ann Bangs, regarding her misconduct at school. He threatens that she will invoke his unending displeasure. If she does not improve her behavior he will "convey you to some lone dark Woodland farm, there to a ruff farmer, will bind you, as servant, untill you are eighteen, or as long the law will admit." NOTE: Seidel was the principal of the seminary from 1818-1819 and 1822-1836. Elijah Bangs owned a china shop on North Main Street in Philadelphia.
  - 1830 July 22; 1830 August 12. Isaac McCoy and J[ohnston] Lykins ALS to James Polke; Fayette, Missouri; Prairie Creek, [Indiana?], 2 pages [total]; Remarks on the death of Josephus, relying on religious faith. Received Polke's letter offering to purchase McCoy's farm, and is sending Lykins to finalize the sale. Preparing to return west to survey Delaware lands above the Kauzau River. "I shall be attended by a guard of Indians." Passage of the Indian bill is gratifying to missionaries such as McCoy, and prospects have never been more promising. Need more missionaries. Includes a note from Lykins explaining his failure to attend to the sale of McCoy's farm and arranging to do so at a later date.
  - 1830 October 16. Andrew Jackson AL to [Philip G.] Randolph; s.l., 1 page; To the acting Secretary of War. Enclosing a letter from the Governor of Massachusetts requesting a loan of surveying equipment. [Gov. of Mass. letter not present].
  - 1830 November 14. W. ALS to Mr. Lamb; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 8 pages; Notes the decline of popular interest in theater and how "Theatrical taste is getting exceedingly bad." Blames the great number of theaters for spreading acting talent too thinly. Believes the low price of admission draws a less sophisticated crowd, driving the decline in theatrical tastes. Comments on the appeal of high versus vulgar theater. Gives advice about what types of productions to show on different nights of the week, not forcing actors to sing, being judicious in using stars, and reigning in actors' improvisation and romantic displays on the stage. Discusses how to avoid distractions from the performances' illusions. Quotes from John Dryden. Advice to a beginning stage manager. Author could possibly be William Burke Wood (1779-1861), William Warren (1767-1832), or Francis Courtney Wemyss (1797-1859).
  - 1830 December 24. W[illiam] G[ardner] Angel ALS to Russell G. Dorr; Washington, [D.C.], 4 pages; Discusses his recent election and the narrow margin of his majority. "... I have always remarked thro life that I have lost more friends and become more obnoxious by an excercise of plain honest dealing than I did by shuffling & deceit." No suitable positions are available for the president to appoint Dorr to, and advises Dorr to refrain from entering politics at all. Political offices prove financially and morally bankrupting. "Vicissitudes are so great and changes so frequent that the continuance of an office when once bestowed is so frail and uncertain that the incumbent lives in constant fear of being turned out, He loses his native independence and becomes a fawning sycophant ever ready to kiss the foot of him who is in power... The idle and extravagant habits acquired by office holders leads them unerringly to poverty and totally unfits them for other avocations." Advises Dorr to be "honest and faithful" with his clients and to be "content with small & certain gains and do not enter upon political life till you have secured a competence of lucre."
  - 1830 December 31. H[enry] D. B[ird] ALS to R[obert] M[ontgomery] Bird; Port Clinton, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Comments on Robert's latest play and it being "given to F.," likely referring to Edwin Forrest (1806-1872), the actor. Discusses awaiting public reactions. Muses on names for "Yr. Fanatick," possibly a character. Worried that the topic is "too ticklish for your 2nd play. Religion (particularly in this presbyterian country) is a rather delicate subject for the stage..." Comments on local women and Pennsylvania Dutch girls. Discusses his personal finances.
  - [ca. 1830]. AMs; [Blawenburg, New Jersey], 17 pages; "Constitution of the Blawenburgh Temperance Society." Includes articles of association and list of 226 members, with Rev. Peter Labagh (1773-1858) listed as the first.
  - 1831 May 9. Geo[rge] McDowell & Son ALS to Lawrence Lewis; Baltimore, [Maryland], 1 page; Comments on the costs and details of binding "Rees' Cyclopedia."
  - 1831 September 10. Geo[rge] McDowell & Son ALS to Lawrence Lewis; Baltimore, [Maryland], 1 page; List of costs associated with binding various books, including Rees' Cyclopedia and the Life of Washington. Includes a letter notifying Lewis of the completion of his order and a note from October 3, 1831, certifying payment.
  - 1831 October 17. M[atthe]w Brown Partially printed DS; Canonsburg, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Fund-raising document for Jefferson College describing its history, philosophy, location, and reliance on tuition for funding. Students are expected to perform manual labor on the college farm in addition to their studies. "The object is to promote health and vigor, both of body and mind, to form habits of industry and economy, to impart some practical as well as scientific knowledge of agriculture, gardening, and the mechanic arts, and greatly to reduce the expenses of a college education." Handwritten addition by college President Brown sets forth amounts required to endow a scholar and the benefits associated with doing so; scholarships may be endowed both by individuals and by Sabbath School association. Lists costs of tuition, board, and other expenses.
  - 1832 February 17. Samuel Todd ADS to Asa Fox; Plymouth, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Contract for provision of housing material. Lists details of the materials, its delivery, and costs.
  - 1832 March. F[rancis] P[reston] Blair Printed Doc.; Washington, [D.C.], 1 page; "Proposals for an Extra Globe." Proposal for printing thirty numbers of an "extra Globe" to support Andrew Jackson's reelection. Criticizes his political opponents, noting the hazards they pose to America. "The Champion of an unreasonable Tariff and the Author of Nullification, having no principle in common but a restless ambition, are found united in their efforts to baffle the President in his foreign negotiations, kindle faction in our halls of legislation, and fill our country with discontent and anarchy." Notes the "causeless rejection of our Minister to Great Britain." Calls for subscriptions to the special editions of the Globe.
  - [1832?] July 7. Mary [Wharton] ALS to T[homas] I. Wharton; Bordentown, [New Jersey], 3 pages; Hopes to come home to hear his speech. Heard her first speech this past Fourth of July, "and I am sure you do not wish me to remain with that as a specimen in my head." Comments on the weather, her housing, and sewing a purse. Discusses Fourth of July celebrations, including songs. Many do not respect the local clergyman. Notes many musical residents and the famed "Mr. Waldie," "as distinguished in his way... as the president in his."
  - 1832 July 31. Ch[arle]s Banchen ALS to Tho[ma]s I. Wharton; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Discusses the local cholera epidemic. Tries to allay Wharton's fears. "The cases are, I understand, with the exception of that at the Almshouse, of the ordinary character attributable to irregularity of habit or great imprudence in some particular indulgence, and altogether confined to the class chiefly affected at New York." Philadelphians are remaining calm. "...the streets are as crouded and every one taken up in his own pursuits as tho' no cholera had appeared." Lists the number of cases and deaths.
  - 1832 August 27. Hannah Goodale ALS to John Ayer; Mackinaw, [Michigan], 3 pages; Goodale writes on behalf of Frederick Ayer (1803-1867), John's brother, offering condolences for the death of his father. Reflects on death and religion. Describes Frederick having gone with a trader to live, preach, and establish a school among the Indians at La Point (Madeline Island in Lake Superior). "After he considered it his duty to go he went very cheerfully, for he truly loves the souls of the poor Indians, and seems not to be at home unless he is among them." Comments on the Native American reaction to Frederick at La Pointe and his plain living. "To some people it would be next to banishment to go nine hundred miles into an Indian Country, some of the way almost impassable and settle down among them without one Christian friend, only one white man, and he an Indian wife. But all this your Brother has done cheerfully, accounting himself honoured and esteeming it a favour thus to be a forerunner to prepare the way of the Lord and make his paths straight." Includes extracts from a letter Frederick wrote to her from Sault Ste. Marie, commenting on religious gains there and his travels.
  - 1832 November 16. Alden Bradford Partially printed DS to [Sheriff of Bristol County]; New Bedford, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Sheriff of Bristol County ordered to "attach the goods or estate of Frederic P. Taber of said Fairhaven painter," or arrest Taber to answer for the debts owed to James Bosworth, Jr., "portrait painter." Regarding the arrest of Tabor for indebtedness in Bosworth v. Tabor. Alden is the Judge of Fairhaven County, Massachusetts writing on behalf of James Bosworth. Includes manuscript note signed by Benja[min] T. Sisson, Deputy Sheriff, "the within precept satisfied-- and have charg my fees to Deft."
  - 1833 May 11. David Butler ALS; Troy, [New York], 2 pages; Asks for help with a young man, Houghton, whose scholarship has been supported "by those who are not his relations" because of his family's poverty. After having "fallen into rather profligate company" at Union College, he lost the financial support of his benefactors. Wishes to mend his ways. Hopes he and Mr. Kirk may have some way of employing the boy, as "it may perhaps be the means of preserving his from ruin." Asks for a copy of his "discourses to young men" to use with the boy.
  - 1833 June 14. Thomas Moore ALS to G[ilbert] S. Newton; Sloperton [Cottage, England], 1 page; "Thanks, my dear Newton, to Mrs. N. and yourself for the pretty waltz, which I play over often to remind me of that agreeable evening, and those sweet Transatlantic tones, in which ‘like a wizard, by a spell / of my own teaching, I was caught.'"
  - 1833 July 16. W[illia]m Wirt ALS to William Rawle; White Sulphur Springs, Virginia, 4 pages; Comments on lands he purchased in Florida several years ago. Provides a detailed proposal and experiment to use destitute German immigrants, recruited in northern cities, as labor in southern states. Notes concerns about the climate and German immigrants' reputation of breaking indentures. Describes the recent German immigrant population and their good character. Wrote up "a plan of association," had a German clergyman translate it, and distributed it amongst immigrant families. Notes his obligations to set up and equip the workers and his son-in-laws' labor directing work and sending the produce to market. Workers split a third of the profits. Intends to grow cotton but may expand to sugar. "I reserve to myself the right of encreasing the colony at pleasure, but with white and consequently free labour only, there being an express stipulation against the introduction of slave or coloured labour."
  - 1833 August 9. Seargent [Smith Prentiss] ALS to George L. Prentiss; Vicksburg, [Mississippi], 3 pages; Letter from Seargent to his brother apologizing for writing so infrequently. Pleased that George enjoys college and advises him to study oration to supplement his academics, explaining in detail the importance of such an endeavor. "This attainment is to every man of the utmost importance. In fact, it is no less than the power of using his other attainments - for of what advantage is information - unless one has the power of conveying it - and shewing to the world that one possesses it..." Discusses how elocution brings men to greatness. Uses Henry Clay (1777-1852) as an example. "...his superiority consists in the power & adroitness with which he brings his information to bear."
  - 1834 February 17. Almira H[art] L[incoln] Phelps ALS; AL to [Zilpah Polly Banister] Grant; Guilford, Vermont, 5 pages [total]; Asks Ipswich Academy Headmistress Grant, as a "distinguished teacher," to write recommendations of her textbooks, Lectures on Botany and Lectures to Young Ladies, for the publisher. Revising her Child's Geography and asks Grant's opinion about female education in Geology and Greek. "I have long thought we ought to direct our pupils more to the contemplation of nature in her various forms than we have been accustomed to do." Working on a "Chemistry for Beginners." Phelps is trying to address "some of the deficiencies I have formerly felt, and which Teachers now complain of with respect to School Books." Would like teachers' feedback. Enclosed is an anonymous letter to be read to the "little ones." Tells of writing songs and visiting a public school closing exercise in which the writer joined them in reciting. Sang in classrooms. Tells a fanciful tale of a mouse inhabiting her boot while she napped.
  - 1834 March. John Ford ALS to Timothy R. Green; Saratoga Springs, [New York], 1 page; Letter soliciting business for the Pavilion Hotel in Saratoga Springs, "calculated expressly for Families & parties." Includes a description of the hotel accommodations and an apology for not having had apartments to suit Green the previous year.
  - 1834 June 30. W[illiam] Strickland ALS to James Mitchell and Robert McCoy; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 1 page; Recommends John Kenworthy, "a painter & glazier in my employ."
  - 1834 June 30. G. ALS to Henry B. Curtiss; Verona, [New York], 3 pages; Was unable to visit due to pleurisy and attending a select school. Studying made his health suffer, so he has turned to farming. Notes his brother working as a carpenter and joiner. Comments on farming and land in Verona. Discusses business failures and scarcity of money. "Much is said about the U.S. Bank as the cause of distressing the Country, as also concerning the President of the U.S. both have here Friends and Enemies as in most parts of the Union." Describes local sect of "Perfectionists" who "pretend to be equal with Christ having power to work miracles, yet cautious how they attempt it as I have not heard of their performing any such deeds." Notes the upheaval they have caused in drawing church members away and proclaiming their desire to "break down & ultimately destroy the churches of the present day." The area may be rid of them soon, as they propose moving west, "where you may possibly be blest with them in Ohio."
  - 1835 January 1 - 1835 February 28. Journal; [Maine], 56 pages; Detailed "slice of life" journal with marginal illustrations, seemingly kept by a barber but with many references to women and women's work. Potpourri of topics, including social visits, women's and agricultural labor, religion, reading, religion, weather, death and health, cleaning and food preparation, tailoring, sewing, schools. Includes multiple drawings of straight-edge razors and references to getting and giving shaves. Describes reading the Bible, newspapers, periodicals, and novels. Notes the "Bank War" with U.S. Banks and the Treasury, federal land grants, and fires in New York City. Many fine pen and ink illustrations provide more details on the day's occurrences. Illustrations include razors, scissors, irons, buckets, a casket, manicules, clothing, people warming feet in hot water, clothes being washed, barrels, the moon, a mole, a musical instrument, an ax and grinder, kettles, wash tubs, baking and food, a goat, letters, logs being pulled, a butchered calf and a fish, a hearth, an umbrella, and a heart with arrows. [References Lydia Haskell, in need of new housing, create separate finding aid]
  - 1835 January 29. Isaac McCoy ALS to James Polke; Westport, Missouri, 4 pages [total]; Writes about sickness and death in their families. Includes religious reflections. Discusses financial matters relating to a land transfer. Sending a copy of his "Annual Register of Indian Affairs" [not included]. Had asked a cousin to "write all that he could recollect of former doings of, and with the Indians." Written on free sheet of prospectus for Isaac M'Coy's Indian Advocate. "PROPOSALS for publishing, on the Kauzau river, within the Indian Territory, west of the state of Missouri, and three hundred miles west of St. Louis, a semi-monthly periodical, to be entitled, THE INDIAN ADVOCATE, Devoted chiefly to Indian Affairs."
  - 1835 May 15. W[illiam] H[enry] Channing ALS to Julia M. Allen [Channing]; Havre, [France], 4 pages; Grateful for a safe sea voyage. Beautiful letter to his future wife, thinking of their future life together and their courtship thus far. Reflects on whether she wants to be his soul's keeper and to aid him in his work "of moral reformation, of human salvation." "Remember you are free - wholly free, as free in my view as if we had never explained to each other the labyrinth of causeless anxieties, in which our hearts have been entangled... that I was indeed candid in my conversations with you, candid to the degree of folly and presumption - both in what I said relative to you and our intercourse, and my own character and prospects..." Briefly mentions books he left for her to read.
  - 1835 May 18. Richard Stanton ALS to Lawrence Lewis; Alexandria, [Virginia], 2 pages [total]; Letter concerning construction details of Washington's tomb. Stereoscope view of tomb, of later date, is included. Enclosed: James MacPherson ALS to Richard Stanton; Baltimore, Maryland, 1p. May 18, 1835. Apologizes for misunderstandings about the tomb's dimensions. Includes pen and pencil sketch of Washington's tomb. Letter accompanied by Alexander Gardner stereoscope view of the tomb.
  - 1835 July 25. A. Scofield ALS to Eliphalet Nott; Auburn, [New York], 3 pages; Letter regarding the question of admitting an African American young man into college. "He is a sensible, decent boy, well prepared to enter sophomore in any college in the land is anxious to enjoy the advantages of regular collegiate courses under your administration." Could be admitted at a school in Hudson, Ohio, but would prefer not to. "... when I think of Africa and her wrongs and the present condition of her exiled sons I feel as though it was time for humanity to awake and put on strength and moderation and wisdom and energy for in regards to this whole matter great events for good or ill are to follow in quick succession. And if the wise fail to act, fools cannot be restrained..."
  - 1835 October 19. Jacob Abbott ALS to John S. C. Abbott; Roxbury, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Writes regarding John's recent move and construction on a church. Would like to speak to him about "the Magazine," but his presence is not required. Gives a detailed account of everything he did that day. Mentions steel plates, proofs, and an engraver.